Guide to the Julius Hemphill Papers MSS.542
Fales Library and Special Collections
Julius Hemphill Papers
1938-2007
Fales Library and Special Collections
Hemphill, Julius
MSS.542
22.5 linear feet in 5 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 10 oversize flat boxes, and 3 small flat boxes
98 audiocassettes
11 videocassettes (vhs)
1.04 Terabytes
9 film reels
1 sound tape reels
Julius Hemphill was a jazz composer and saxophone player who helped found the World Saxophone Quartet. He was a founder of the World Saxophone Quartet, the Julius Hemphill Quartet, and the Julius Hemphill Sextet. Hemphill's compositions and arrangements are noted for their combination of jazz, blues, and big-band sound. This collection consists of materials created and collected by Julius Hemphill from the mid-1960s to 1995 documenting Hemphill's career as a jazz composer and saxophonist. Materials in this collection include personal correspondence, original writings, ephemera, and manuscript music in various formats and stages of completion, including composition notebooks, scores, and parts to compositions. The manuscript music consists of compositions by Hemphill in his hand, compositions prepared by professional copyists, and arrangements and re-compositions of works by Hemphill of other composers. The collection also includes audio and video recordings of Hemphill's concert recordings, rehearsals, and interviews of Hemphill from radio broadcasts.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created and collected by Julius Hemphill from the mid-1960s to 1995 documenting Hemphill's career as a jazz composer and saxophonist. Materials in this collection include personal correspondence, original writings, ephemera, and manuscript music in various formats and stages of completion, including composition notebooks, scores, and parts to compositions. The manuscript music consists of compositions by Hemphill in his hand, compositions prepared by professional copyists, and arrangements and re-compositions of works by Hemphill of other composers. The collection also includes audio and video recordings of Hemphill's concert recordings and rehearsals on audiocassette, reel-to-reel tapes, optical discs, VHS cassettes, and other formats. The audio recordings also include interviews of Hemphill from radio broadcasts.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ursula Oppens in June and July 2018, and February 2020; the accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2018.086, 2018.112, and 2020.028.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Biographical Note
Julius Hemphill (1938-1995) was a jazz composer and saxophone player who helped found the World Saxophone Quartet. Hemphill was born in Fort Worth, Texas, and served in the United States Army for several years beginning in 1964. He began playing the clarinet, studying under John Carter, before learning saxophone. Hemphill later moved to St. Louis, Missouri and co-founded the Black Artists' Group (BAG) arts collective. He moved to New York City in the 1970s and became an active member of the city's jazz community, performing, recording, and teaching other musicians. He was a founder of the World Saxophone Quartet, the Julius Hemphill Quartet, and the Julius Hemphill Sextet. Hemphill's compositions and arrangements are noted for their combination of jazz, blues, and big-band sound.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in alphabetical order.
Jazz musicians -- United States; African American jazz musicians; Saxophonists; Scores.; Julius Hemphill Big Band; Julius Hemphill Quartet; Julius Hemphill Sextet
- About Itself, 1968-1995; cuid20396 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Guitar and cello part to a fourteen-measure composition, not in Hemphill's hand.
- Abstrac, 1968-1995; cuid20397 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Nineteen-page holograph score, ruled by hand, orchestrated for a jazz big band (five woodwinds, three trumpets, French horn, trombone, tuba, cello, bass, and percussion).
- Affairs of the Heart, 1980-1995; cuid20398 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Professionally copied parts to a work for saxophone quartet, orchestrated using woodwind doubles (soprano saxophone, flute, alto flute, bass clarinet).
- After The Crowd, 1978-1995; cuid20399 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Five-page score photocopied from Sightation Notebook for a work for clarinet, French horn, saxophone, bass, and drums. Sightation Notebook includes an ordered list of the suite of compositions with circus-themed titles, from which this piece is drawn.
- Ahmad the Terrible, 1986-1995; cuid20400 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Holograph concert score. Sixty-three-measure big-band arrangement of a Jack DeJohnette composition dedicated to pianist Ahmad Jamal. The folder also includes a holograph score for backgrounds during the solo section from measure 63, with detailed notes to the copyist in red ink. The melody of the original DeJohnette composition is not notated in the score.
- Air Rings, 1968-1995; cuid20401 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Score in holograph for a work in two voices in treble and bass clef. There is a treble melody line, first designated for flute, but then suggested for soprano saxophone 8vb. The bass clef part is mostly single notes, though double stops may indicate a cello. There are also professionally copied soprano saxophone and bass parts, as well as parts in holograph for trumpet and guitar. The piece has an eight-bar intro, a twenty-bar A section, repeated, and an eight-bar bridge.
- Anchorman - from "Last Supper", 1990-1990; cuid20402 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Photocopy of professionally copied parts for saxophone sextet (two soprano, alto, two tenor, and baritone), based on material from "The Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land."
- Anchorman - Theatrical Piece, 1968-1995; cuid20403 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Holograph score in pencil of a piece for trumpet, two tenor saxophones, and bass clarinet. Score is in five lines, with meticulous phrase markings. Pages 4 and 5 (of 10 indicated) are missing. This piece was written for "Anchorman," a theatrical work in two acts by Paul Carter Harrison. Folder also includes a shorter score, marked "Act I," orchestrated for soprano saxophone, trumpet, tenor saxophone, and bass clarinet.
- Another Feeling, 1981-1995; cuid20404 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Professionally copied parts for a saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone). Composition is part of a suite entitled "Wind/Rhythms" written for World Saxophone Quartet's collaboration with Max Roach's M'Boom. This work is a slow chorale. See "Wind/Rhythms" for full score.
- Answer, The, 1991-1995; cuid20405 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Transposed holograph score in pencil of a piece for saxophone sextet (soprano, two altos, two tenors, baritone). Twenty-one measures. Hemphill wrote this work as a concert piece for the Julius Hemphill Saxophone Sextet; folder includes set of manuscript parts not in composer's hand and professionally copied parts use for the Sextet folio published by Subito Music.
- Antecedent, 1977-1995; cuid20406 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Photocopy of "Fourth Blues: Uttered Flute" (a title in a decorative compartment) from Foran Notebook. An improvised flute solo, this piece was included on the album Blue Boyé (1977) under the title "Antecedent."
- Ascension, 1990-1995; cuid20407 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Professionally copied parts to a piece for saxophone sextet (two sopranos, alto, two tenors, baritone) originally written for "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land."
- Astrid, 1968-1995; cuid20408 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Holograph score in pencil for an up-tempo piece orchestrated for soprano saxophone, guitar, bass, and drums. It is eighteen measures long with a written tag; the form is AABA + tag. Score is annotated with phone numbers and addresses for different individuals. Folder also includes professionally copied parts.
- At Dr. King's Table, 1990-1995; cuid20409 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone sextet (soprano, two alto, two tenor, and baritone). See "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land" for additional score and parts.
- At Harmony - Small group, 1984-1995; cuid20410 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Holograph score for a work for alto saxophone and cello. Folder also includes a score in holograph for alto saxophone, guitar, bass, and drums, with detailed notes to the copyist, as well as a holograph alto saxophone part and a photocopy of a trumpet part from Trumpet Notebook.
- At Harmony - Big band parts, 1984-1995; cuid20411 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Full set of parts, professionally copied, on paper and transparency (paper vellum). Folder includes photocopies of parts (some originals in "Aggregated Parts").
- At Harmony - Big band score, 1984-1995; cuid20412 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Holograph score in pencil as well as several photocopies.
- Band Theme, 1993-1995; cuid20413 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Holograph score in pencil for saxophone sextet (soprano, two altos, two tenors, baritone), titled "Backgrounds Band Theme." This piece was written for Julius Hemphill Sextet and was included in "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera." Parts were improvised during the tenor saxophone solo based on Jimmy Heath's "CTA" chord changes.
- Basso / Pro Bird, 1968-1995; cuid20414 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Score with professionally-copied parts for a piece for flute, bass, and drums. Vellum and light-sensitive paper. Includes note for copyist that a guitar part should be made. The piece is eighteen measures long, with intro in 7/4 and main section in 2/2. Hemphill's notes indicate that a portion of this composition is used in the eighth movement of the "Drunk on God" suite. That movement is titled "Mailika" on the album Julius Hemphill Big Band (1988); it is titled "Maliaka: Drum / Woman" in Hemphill's score.
- Bayou Sketch, 1977-1995; cuid20415 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Four parts in holograph for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, baritone). Included on the album Point of No Return (1977) as "Bajou Scetches" (and attributed to Hamiet Bluiett).
- Big Band, 1968-1995; cuid20416 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Photocopy of a holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for a piece for big band (flute, alto saxophone / clarinet, alto/tenor saxophone, tenor/alto saxophone / flute, baritone saxophone / clarinet, bass clarinet / tenor saxophone / piccolo, French horn, trombone, tuba, cello, bass, and two percussion parts).
- Big Drum Speaks, The, 1988-1995; cuid20417 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Parts in holograph for two guitars and bass (the instrumentation of Hemphill's JAH band), with chord symbols in a different hand. The parts are from a movement in the suite "Drunk on God," which appears on the album Julius Hemphill Big Band (1988). The movement is titled "Cosmic Country Boy" on the recording. See "Drunk on God" for parts and score, with title sometimes as "From Out of Nowhere: The Big Drum Speaks."
- Big Foot, 1977-1995; cuid20418 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Holograph score and parts for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, baritone).
- Bimbo: The Elephant, 1977-1995; cuid20419 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Sightation Notebook of a work for clarinet, trumpet, alto saxophone, bass, and drums. Sightation Notebook includes an ordered list of the suite of compositions with circus-themed titles, from which this piece is drawn.
- Bitter Glory, A: Opening Song, 1994-1995; cuid20420 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Two-page holograph score for a piece with a soprano or alto vocal line and unorchestrated accompaniment. In pencil and black ink with annotations in red ink; photocopies include further annotations. Several manuscript notebooks include parts for this piece for reeds/woodwinds (soprano and alto saxophone, clarinet, flute), brass (trumpet, French horn, trombone), cello, and bass. The piece is the "Opening Song" from music written for the theater piece "A Bitter Glory."
- Blessed Quietness, 1968-1995; cuid20421 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Photocopy of parts in holograph for trumpet and tenor saxophone. Identified as page 2; page 1 not in folder.
- Blues Country, 1968-1995; cuid20422 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Bass and guitar parts (each one page) in holograph of a twenty-one measure piece. Musik Hug Notebook has a score that includes a partial part for saxophone (included in folder as a photocopy).
- Bordertown (San Antonio), 1980-1995; cuid20423 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Holograph score in pencil, with annotations in red ink, of a big-band arrangement dated 1980. There are further additions in Hemphill's hand, with background parts and harmonizations corresponding to the album Julius Hemphill Big Band (1988). The folder also includes a saxophone quartet arrangement (soprano, soprano/alto, bass clarinet / tenor saxophone, alto clarinet / baritone saxophone), as well as professionally copied parts; the first page (of two) for the bass clarinet / tenor saxophone part is missing. Folder includes a piano score in holograph for "Bordertown," with the the annotation "Good Boye Music ASCAP" on each page.
- Bordertown - Big band parts I, 1980-1995; cuid20424 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Professionally copied parts for big-band arrangement, reflecting some changes of instrumentation between 1980 and 1988 versions.
- Bordertown - Big band parts II, 1980-1995; cuid20425 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Paper vellum parts and photocopies for the 1980 big-band arrangement.
- Bumpkin, 1968-1995; cuid20426 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, baritone).
- Buster Bee, 1978-1995; cuid20427 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Folder includes Hemphill's alto saxophone part in holograph, as well as a photocopy from Schirmer's Notebook of the melody line for a duet for two alto saxophones. The holograph alto saxophone part includes some harmony notes to the melody found in Schirmer's Notebook.
- BZ, 1968-1995; cuid20428 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Photocopy of incomplete score from Schirmer's Notebook for an enlarged big band ensemble (piccolo, flute, clarinet, alto, tenor and baritone saxophones, three trumpets, trombones, cello, bass, and percussion.) Score includes sketch for fourteen-measure intro, followed by twenty measures of a soprano saxophone part with some chord symbols.
- C. M. E., 1977-1995; cuid20429 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Photocopy of a holograph score from Foran Notebook, for a work for flute, soprano saxophone, and alto saxophone, recorded through an overdub process on the album Blue Boyé (1977). The piece is titled "C.M.E." on the album and "Seventh (Roots)" in the notebook.
- C (Those Blues) - Big band score, 1974-1995; cuid20430 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Big band arrangement in holograph score in pencil, with annotations in red ink, as performed in 1980. There is an additional page in holograph with material that was used for the album Julius Hemphill Big Band (1988). Folder includes several photocopies of the big band score. This piece has been variously titled "C," "C (Those Blues)," and "C/Saw."
- C (Those Blues) - Big band parts, 1974-1995; cuid20431 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Professionally copied parts for the big band arrangement, on paper vellum and paper.
- Capetown Harvest, 1968-1995; cuid20432 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Viola part in holograph, with title written in black felt-tip pen.
- Changes, 1968-1995; cuid20433 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Photocopy of score, possibly in Hemphill's hand, with written instructions in Hemphill's hand, for flute, baritone saxophone, cello, and drums. The piece is forty-six measures long and is based on the main motive of Buddy Miles's composition "Changes." The piece may be incomplete, as there is a letter "D" following the fermata in measure 46.
- Children's Song, The - Saxophone quartet version, 1975-1995; cuid20434 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Alto clarinet part, probably in Hamiett Bluiett's hand, which transposes the clarinet part from a work orchestrated for two flutes, clarinet, and tenor saxophone; a photocopy of the holograph score for from Foran Notebook is included here. Folder also includes a trombone part by a professional copyist on paper vellum, indicating performances by a different ensemble.
- Children's Song, The - Sextet version, 1990-1995; cuid20435 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  One-page holograph score for saxophone sextet (three altos, two tenors, baritone) and voice (dancers onstage), in which Hemphill harmonizes the opening melody of his saxophone quartet of the same title. The folder also includes professionally copied parts for soprano, two altos, tenor, and baritone saxophone. (A second tenor part may be missing.) Folder includes photocopy of holograph score, as well as a different orchestration for alto saxophone, trumpet, tenor saxophone, trombone, baritone saxophone, and bass. This was the final movement of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land." See "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land" for score and parts.
- Choo Choo, 1975-1995; cuid20436 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook and several sets of photocopied parts, also in composer's hand, of a piece for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, baritone).
- Circles, 1968-1995; cuid20437 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  One-page holograph score for an unfinished piece for saxophone quartet (two altos, tenor, baritone). In pencil and black ink with annotations in red ink. Nine-bar intro, eight-bar A section, and an eight-bar B section consisting only of baritone saxophone melody.
- Cole, Bill: Compositions arranged by Hemphill, 1986-1995; cuid20438 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Holograph score of arrangements for an octet (two woodwinds, trumpet, tuba, cello, bass, and two percussionists) of seven compositions by Bill Cole. In pencil and black ink with further annotations in red and blue ink, fifteen pages in total. Piece titles: "To Sow Is To Reap," "Live with Humble Man /Spirit," "Tormenter," "Beat Drum / Man Man," "One Man's Hatred / Destiny," "Don't Go to Bed With Your Roof Afire," "Man Woman Snake Dead." Folder includes envelope in which scores were mailed from Cole to Hemphill.
- Connections, 1980-1995; cuid20439 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Parts in holograph of a piece for saxophone quartet (two altos, tenor, baritone). The piece is a 34-measure slow chorale.
- Cool Red, 1987-1995; cuid20440 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Holograph score for a piece for saxophone quartet (two sopranos, tenor, baritone). Ballad in 3/4 time.
- Coral, 1968-1995; cuid20441 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Two-page holograph score in black ink for a piece orchestrated for flute, trumpet, and cello. Folder includes holograph parts for cello and trumpet. The piece is twelve measures long, with a four-bar vamp at the end.
- Countryside, 1977-1995; cuid20442 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook of a piece entitled "Fifth Blues," orchestrated for flute, soprano saxophone, and alto saxophone. This piece appears on the album Blue Boyé (1977) with the title "Countryside."
- Crystal, 1968-1995; cuid20443 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  One-page holograph score, eleven measures long, along with photocopy of score that includes additional tempo marking in composer's hand, of a composition for string quartet (violin, viola, cello, double bass). Instruction for "cymball roll" suggests the piece originally included percussion.
- Cyclic Affair, 1968-1995; cuid20444 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Cello part in holograph.
- Dar El Sudan, 1977-1977; cuid20445 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Four parts in holograph of piece for saxophone quartet (two soprano, tenor, and baritone).
- Dear Friend, 1968-1995; cuid20446 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Score in holograph of piece for three instruments, likely alto saxophone, cello, and an unknown third instrument. The score is fifteen measures long, with three unidentified parts; lowest line indicates "arco" at times. There are two parts in Hemphill's hand for alto saxophone and cello, though they do not correspond precisely to the lower two staves in the full score.
- Dimples: The Fat Lady on Parade, 1978-1995; cuid20447 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Photocopy of score in composer's hand from Sightation Notebook for clarinet, soprano saxophone, trumpet, bass, and drums. Sightation Notebook includes an ordered list of the suite of compositions with circus-themed titles, from which this piece is drawn.
- Dirty Row, 1977-1995; cuid20448 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  Photocopy of score in composer's hand from Foran Notebook, recorded as an overdub composition on the album Blue Boyé (1977). In the notebook, it is titled "Fifth Blues." Score consists of several twelve-tone rows with transpositions.
- Dogon A.D. - Small Group, 1972-1995; cuid20449 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Kawaida Notebook, entitled "Original Dogon A.D," for alto saxophone, trumpet, vibraphone, and drums. Various parts for alto saxophone, trumpet, cello, bass, tuba, bass clarinet, and guitar, reflecting different group arrangements. Some parts are in holograph, others professionally copied, and others in different hands.
- Dogon A.D. - Big Band, 1980-1995; cuid20450 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Score in holograph for big-band arrangement of "Dogon A.D.", orchestrated for five saxophones, trumpet, French horn, trombone, tuba, vibraphone, bass, and drums. There is a complete set of professionally copied parts on paper vellum and paper for this twelve-piece arrangement, as well as a part in holograph for guitar, with annotation in composer's hand. See large-scale work "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera" for an arrangement with added strings.
- Downstairs, 1968-1995; cuid20451 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Cello part in holograph for a seventy-measure piece.
- Dreams, 1968-1995; cuid20452 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Score in holograph for one unidentified instrument, apparently torn from manuscript book. Tempo marking is "Very slow" and the piece is divided into "Part I" and "Part II."
- Dream / Scheme, 1978-1995; cuid20453 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Photocopies of parts in composer's hand for two flutes, soprano and tenor saxophone. Holograph full score appears in Foran Notebook.
- Dung, 1978-1995; cuid20454 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  Various parts for clarinet, alto saxophone, trumpet, tuba, bass, drums, and guitar, some in holograph, others professionally copied. There are two incomplete scores, both indicating a quintet arrangement, one in holograph with lines for tuba, bass, and drums, the other a photocopy from Sightation Notebook for clarinet, alto saxophone, and trumpet. Sightation Notebook includes an ordered list of the suite of compositions with circus-themed titles, from which this piece is drawn.
- East / West Cycles, 1968-1995; cuid20455 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Photocopy of trumpet part in composer's hand. Sixteen-measure melody.
- Ebony, 1986-1995; cuid20456 (Box 5, Folder 9)